Now we know when Walmart and Dollar
General really start doing well, that's
not a good sign for consumers or the
overall economy, particularly when it's
higher income shoppers that are coming
flooding into those stores. But when
that traffic starts to spill over to the
local pawn shop, that's a whole other
level. We're talking about canaries in
coal mines here. But here's the thing,
we're not only seeing that happen, the
data, including a whole bunch that we
got today, is backing it up. More
negative real incomes and a plunging
savings rate that has suburban women
using their jewelry as collateral for
short-term pawn shop loans. It really is
the Walmart signal only one step further
into distress. Trading down to discount
stores is one thing, but having to hawk
personal items to be able to pay for
groceries and gasoline is not what you
want to see for the overall economy. The
latest figures from the Bureau of
Economic Analysis explain perfectly why
this is happening more and more.
Price-adjusted private incomes, which is
the best proxy working economy, they
declined once again in March, which is
the second straight contraction, the
third in four months, and the fourth
time over the last half year. It was
enough to turn the six-month change
there negative by the most in years, a
rare signal of distress, which proves
which proves consumers are falling
further and further behind as the lack
of income once again clashes with rising
expenses just starting with gasoline.
And because Americans are paying more
for gas and not getting paid enough to
absorb that hit, their savings rate
plunged to 3.6%, which is the lowest in
3 and 1/2 years. Thus, Walmart, Dollar
General, and now collateralized pawn
shop loans.
When there aren't enough jobs, there's
just not going to be enough income. It's
the same forgot how to grow story only
with jobs now being lost, and then along
comes an energy shock to make everything
that much more difficult. And keep this
in mind as we go forward here. The BEA
data, the income statistics, are just
for the month of March.
kind of shudder to think what they might
be in April though. I would wager a
guess the pawn shops already know.
Now you always want to be careful with
individual stories, even when it's not
just one or another. The old adage is
that the plural of anecdotes is not data
and that remains true. But in this case,
we start with the story that builds upon
others that we've seen and then get the
data which backs everything up. Now
we've been talking about Walmart and the
Walmart boom for over a year now. When
flat beverage first showed up, which
just means demand for workers among
employers dropped low enough some
businesses went beyond their hiring
freezes and started to cut back on the
number of employees. That's where the
negative payroll months really came in.
And when all that started last year,
Walmart's business really took a shine.
It wasn't just the normal hard hit
consumers that they had coming in their
stores. The retail giant was winning
with wealthier Americans, those making a
100K and above. That wasn't just about
job losses. It pointed to the lack of
incomes at all parts of the labor market
spectrum. And Dollar General, they said
the same thing to the point the low end
retailer was undergoing store models to
better cater to the sudden business from
these non-traditional customers. Yet
another anecdotal warning that aligned
with the broader labor statistics,
especially once the establishment survey
was fixed yet again by the QCEW. It is
still astounding to me how everyone or
most everyone in the mainstream anyway
just totally ignores the complete lack
of job growth last year. Entire freaking
calendar year with basically zero net
jobs. That is unheard of outside of NBER
declared yep this thing is really
happening recessions. Again, the data
fits the stories, the one told by
Walmart and Dollar General, not Nvidia
and Open AI.
Now we have the pawn shops coming in and
they are apparently if not booming then
seeing at the very least more robust
business than normal. So let's roll the
tape here.
CEO Michael Goldstein tells me after 40
years in business, he's seeing a shift.
>> Definitely seeing more suburban
customers coming in than we have in the
past.
>> More women than men. Goldstein says
rather than selling items outright,
>> Uh yeah, mostly my jewelry.
>> Many get loans on same items over and
over again. 90% buy their items back
again.
>> My customers basically are working and
they have too much week left at the end
of their paycheck. And then a bill comes
up and they're like, "Oh man, what am I
going to do about this?"
>> I appreciate, you know, getting that few
dollars when I need it.
>> You can actually see when you look at
what is happening in your store, how the
economy's going, even sometimes before
Wall Street. We think about ourselves as
a canary in the coal mine, so to speak.
When that price gas goes up and
unemployment starts to tick up a little
bit, my customers are hurting.
>> You bet you. Bingo. When gas prices go
up and unemployment ticks up, because
there is no job growth at the very
least, suddenly suburban women are using
their jewelry and personal items as
collateral for liquidity management to
bring in a few bucks temporarily in
order to pay that bill they didn't
expect or the one which did show up with
a huge increase that was attached to it.
They really have no savings left, which
is exactly what we're seeing in the data
as we'll see in just a minute. And then
along comes the energy shock. And this
is the real bad part about an energy
shock, because it's something that's
indispensable. We're talking about
gasoline and fuel and energy.
It's not something you can just set
aside or just stop using. You have to
use it. And when the cost goes up,
unless incomes go up, and as we'll see,
they're not, unless incomes go up, you
have only bad choices, including the
pawn shop.
What is a Euro Dollar University
membership? It's where understanding the
monetary world isn't a mystery, it's a
method. If you're serious about your
financial education and you want clarity
in a world of volatility and
misunderstanding,
this is for you.
Mainstream education has left so many
gaps on the most foundational concepts,
making sense of everything is
practically impossible otherwise. With
our memberships, we'll fill in
everything that you've been missing.
Whether you're starting out or
sharpening your edge, our membership
scale with your goals. At Euro Dollar
University, we teach you about how money
really works so that you can evaluate
fundamentals and make grounded
decisions. With a Euro Dollar University
membership, you get a comprehensive
library of foundational and advanced
lectures, in-depth case studies, and
real-world analyses, live Q&A sessions,
regular updates on macro trends, and
even some central bank policies. And
most important, how to interpret
critical derivative market signals you
will not find anywhere else.
You can't be in position to succeed if
you don't know how it all really works
and fits together. So, if you're ready
to explore, master monetary systems both
past and future with structure, clarity,
and confidence. Click the link in the
description to visit
eurodollar.university/memberships
to join us today.
Because it's not just that prices for
those things go up, it's the cost of
something you really can't do without.
It's energy is what economists call
price inelastic. You can't really cut
back on how much you drive. I mean, you
got to get to work or you you end up
risking being the next one let go or
having your hours trimmed even further
than they have been. The kids have got
to go to school. Maybe you can drive a
little bit less for personal stuff or
you try to plan fewer trips to the store
and when running errands, but by and
large, you're stuck. And that's why oil
price shocks are right there ahead of
recessions, especially over the last
half century. You take an economy that's
already in bad shape, that's fragile,
you pour some literal gasoline on the
economic fire, and it just leads to the
bad economic outcomes. So, the only
thing you can do other than pawning your
iPhone or shopping at Walmart is to cut
back your spending on anything else,
especially anything that's
discretionary. Downgrade your vacation
from maybe the trip to the mountains to
just hanging out at home or going to the
local lake. Cut a few more of those
subscriptions that maybe you like, but
you don't use enough to justify the
ongoing expense. It's real
belt-tightening. Taking a more prudent
approach to everything. And we've
already seen this another series of, you
know, anecdotes and data revolving
credit. I brought this up recently. It
might seem counterintuitive at first
given the context, but credit card
borrowers tend to borrow less and even
pay down their balances under these
circumstances. It's another sign of
belt-tightening and it's been happening
already alongside the job losses that go
back over the last year, more than last
year, last couple years. And I expect
we're going to see a lot more of the
same thing moving ahead into summertime.
It always comes back to jobs and
incomes. There's been little to no
hiring for a couple years, which takes
the top off of income growth, then
flatter beverage, the economy starts to
produce layoffs, not a huge number, not
some catastrophic wave like early 2009,
but enough that it pressures the labor
market even more and more consumers feel
that pressure even if they're not the
ones that are being let go. Income
growth that was already insufficient
suddenly becomes a contraction.
And the clearest example of this is
something called real personal income
excluding transfer receipts. It's all
the income that you can get from the
private economy, so no government
payments. It's mainly salaries and
wages, all adjusted for price changes.
So, what the data is showing you is
whether or not the labor market healthy
enough to keep consumers healthy. And
are they seeing enough income over and
above price changes to buy some new
stuff, do some new things, get on some
new services to keep the economy
chugging along? But what you see instead
is it has not been that way in years,
thus forgot how to grow. But then it
took another turn for the worse heading
into 2024 and then yet another one in
2025 to the point now real private
incomes aren't just effectively
contracting, meaning going sideways like
before. And remember, sideways is a
contraction. Anything less than a
minimum growth rate is a contraction. It
means falling further and further
behind. This is why I always show these
data points with trend lines. Think of
the trend line as the minimum growth
rate. Anything less than that minimum is
falling further behind. That's a
contraction. So, private incomes, they
were already well under that line to
begin with from way back in 2022 when
the supply shocks, price changes
basically impoverished everyone. And you
could see it right here, especially
workers. But incomes, they never caught
up, instead falling further and further
behind, which easily explains why voters
are fed up with politicians everywhere.
And this is a global problem. Just ask
every regime, no matter which party is
currently in office. But as job losses
in the US have begun to pile up, even if
it isn't a massive wave of them, it has
been more than enough to turn sideways
contraction over the last year into
outright contraction. In other words,
from falling further and further behind
to really falling behind, from shopping
at Target, then Walmart, then Dollar
General, to now pawning jewelry for some
spare cash to make sure you can still
drive the kids to school and keep the AC
on for the next month at least. The
income data confirms the jobs numbers
and therefore the Walmart warning and
suddenly what's going on with pawn
brokers. Wall Street soars, Main Street
sinks. And the money that is being spent
more recently as we get into the energy
shock in March is being spent just
trying to stay stay afloat with higher
gasoline and energy costs.
So, nominal spending jumped by 9/10 of a
percent in March alone, which is the
biggest monthly gain since the end of
2024, which was another artificial high.
And that's just what this is, a
combination of paying more for gasoline,
front-loading some purchases ahead of
maybe higher cost where possible. And
much of it was supported by the tax
refunds that like incomes are running
behind expectations, not to mention
running behind what's actually needed.
And despite all these temporary boosts,
because it was largely spent trying to
pay higher energy, real personal
consumption expenditures or PCE were
only up 2/10 of a percent in March. So,
it continues a string of weakness in
real terms, meaning adjusting for
prices. But, because income growth has
been worse, that means Americans are
still spending more than they're making
thanks to the flat beverage and no jobs
last year, pitiful labor market,
everyone outside of consumers themselves
just ignored. As a result, the savings
rate tumbled to just 3.6% last month,
which is its lowest level since October
of 2022.
That was when income growth was much
stronger than it is now, but price
changes back then were far outpacing it.
That was the impoverishment. Now,
there's practically no income growth and
just a little extra push in terms of
price changes and boom, savings tumble
with very little of any cushion left for
far too many Americans all across the
macroeconomic landscape. In fact, as
we're seeing their cushion dwindle,
that's Walmart. That's the pawn shop
story that we're getting. As I told you,
the data completely backs up the
anecdotes. And let me remind you one
more time, the data anyway is for March,
not even April, let alone May. This is
one of the ingredients in recessions, a
weak economy, which means flat beverage
that leaves consumers on thin ice.
Therefore, they don't have nearly enough
margin to take another hit or absorb
another shock. And then along comes one
of those, especially for something
that's price inelastic like oil, and it
pushes Main Street right over the edge
and onto the Walmart property after
having gotten some cash, putting up
their wedding ring as collateral at the
local pawn shop. So, you look back at
previous recessions, the savings rate
was down to around 2 and 3% late in 2007
and early 2008. Same time the oil prices
were climbing and of course there was
that whole monetary crisis raging. The
recession followed. The savings rate had
dropped to around 4% in '99 and 2000
with higher gasoline costs right before
the dot-com bust and then the dot-com
recession. Personal savings had fallen
down to around 8% late in '89 and
throughout parts of 1990 when Saddam
Hussein's Kuwaiti misadventure provided
the final straw leading to the '90-'91
S&L recession.
It really is a key point just how
fragile the economy is, especially the
labor market, before the energy shock
comes along and sends everything right
over the edge. But right now, what are
we hearing? We're hearing the exact
opposite. The only word that you hear
out of anyone's mouth, especially in the
mainstream, especially anyone in an
official position, is resilient. The
economy is resilient. It's not fragile,
it's resilient. I mean, J. Powell, his
final press conference yesterday as Fed
chair, he said the economy was
incredibly resilient. But what other
tune is he going to sing in his swan
song? Let's go to the Let's go to the
tape here, too.
>> How do you describe the economy outside
of the misbehaving inflation? I mean,
um,
it's still awfully resilient given all
of the blows.
>> I don't know that you can be awfully
resilient. So, it's actually quite
resilient, I would say, cuz it's a
positive thing if I can if I can have
that amendment. Yeah, that that you
know, growth is really solid across our
economy. Some of that is um that
consumer spending is hanging in pretty
well. The The most recent data are good.
>> You do have to wonder what in the hell
these people are looking at. The most
recent data are good? No. The most
recent data isn't catastrophic,
therefore we're told it must be good.
Those are the only two choices these
people have ever given you. They set up
a straw man that's easily knocked over.
If it isn't crashing like late 2008,
then we must be fine and the Fed must
have done a really good job or whichever
politicians have managed their economic
affairs really well. It is a false
choice, one that you need to reject, one
that is fueling a lot of anger out there
among Americans and voters around the
rest of the world. Stop saying the
economy is resilient. As I just pointed
out, there were no job gains for an
entire calendar year in 2025. And that
followed the year in 2024 when the job
gains were roughly a million short of
where they needed to be. Falling further
further behind to the point that
shoppers are now shopping beyond Walmart
and having to go to the pawn store just
to be able to make ends meet. None of
that is resilient. It's blatant
sickness. It is not good. It's the
opposite of good. But because the only
two choices that you're given, if it
isn't 2009, then everything has to be
fine and resilient. Everybody goes along
with that one, especially at the New
York Stock Exchange.
Because it isn't hundreds of thousands
of jobs being lost every single week and
the macro data is modestly positive
instead of being riddled with big minus
signs, they say it's resilient. For
them, sideways is more than good enough.
But we know sideways is nowhere near
good enough. For everyone else having to
live in this show, sideways is
falling further and further behind.
Sideways and a few negatives is
struggling even harder after half a
freaking decade of struggles already. To
the point that they're now at the pawn
shop. They're completely detached from
reality mostly by plan. They lie to you
about the state of the economy because
they believe it's for your own good. Not
to mention, since we allow the Fed to
grade its own performance, is anyone
really shocked at the grade that J.
Powell hands in? Is A+ resilient. Of
course, all the financial media eat this
slop up. They take every word he says as
the gospel truth. If it isn't crashing,
it must be resilient.
Meanwhile, Walmart's booming and
suburban moms are pawning their laptops
so they can go down to Dollar General
just so their kids don't see any
downside. But the stock market. Never
forget the stock market. Wall Street is
soaring as Main Street soured. They must
be selling shares in pawn shops.
Want some more anecdotes as well as data
that backs it up? Look no further than
European banks. Now, European central
banks, European banks, though Canadian
central banks is a little bit closer to
the truth and all of that in the video
link below. As always, thank you very
much for joining me. Huge thank you Euro
dollar University members and
subscribers and until next time, take
care.